[Music]
hello everyone welcome to actin flap
live stream number 46.2
it's june 22 2022
welcome to the actin flap we're a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links on the slide
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome
and will follow video etiquette for live
streams
head over to
activeinference.org to learn about
participating in
live streams or in the many other active
lab projects
we're here in our third discussion on
the paper
active inference models do not
contradict folk psychology by smith
ramstead and kiefer we had a zero
with ryan joining
and jakub and dean where we talked
through some of the background of this
paper
and last week in the dot one
we
had a great discussion went a lot of
ways as dot ones do
and opened up some threads to continue
discussing in this dot two
i know each of you have some
things to bring up there's also a few
key sections of the paper that we
haven't gone into in much detail
so there'll be a lot to do in the dot
two and of course everybody watching
live is also welcome to
make comments
we'll start with uh just an introduction
and warm-up
we
can say hi and add anything else that
we're looking forward to talking about
or to reducing our uncertainty about
through today's discussion or maybe even
if it's not too early where we'd like to
be heading as we
take off on this dot 2 and leave the 46
series how does it
result results in us being different
thinking differently acting differently
in the rest of our
post-46 lives
so
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california
and
just a conversation with dean before we
began about some other
core concepts
other than beliefs desires and
intentions
so what other acronym models could we
use
what other kinds of models are
consistent or
where else can active inference be
providing us extra information or
utility
and a few other things and i'll pass it
to dean
hey stanley i'm dean here in calgary um
i think what i'm
i'm curious about is a couple of things
as i said i'm i'm curious about things
are behaviors that appear to be targeted
versus
behaviors that appear to be non-targeted
and there was some there was
there's some reference to that in this
paper
the other thing as i said i'm kind of
curious about is
this
moving to the place of saying that
active inference has these different
types
be it extended or
decision making or motor active imprints
and what the implications of that are
i mean bottom line for me is i think if
we can
operationalize that word
um
through active inference that
it shouldn't be difficult to figure out
that that applies to behaviors that
there's operations
grounding a lot of behavior so
yeah that's what i'm kind of curious
about the outpatient to uh give it
great to be back uh it's my second time
on here really uh appreciate this i'm on
33 so i've listened through lecture 33
so i'm almost
caught up to uh
the current i look forward to having
daniel on my channel
friday 4 p.m
eastern time
you know there's so much to active
inference because it's your useful
framework for
countless different fields and
specifically related to this i had you
know definitely thoughts and then how do
we look at the
mechanics of the equation
versus
you know we call folks ecology but uh i
would put that generally into uh what i
would call introspection i have a
background in theology
and uh yes i've thought a lot about
introspection
and trying to match
what we see through various methods of
introspection
and
you know maybe where the science and
mathematics is leading us
and also i guess the field of
psychometrics that isn't necessarily
introspection but it may or may not uh
match uh the equations and then how do
we describe the phenomenon uh you
understand them or maybe they're not
descriptibles and that we describe them
with the mathematical equations and
there's not really any good way to uh
translate that into uh words that would
be
you know understandable to uh
your folk uh common people in in that
way
awesome ali
uh hi i'm ali i'm an independent
researcher from iran
i'm very glad to be here and i'm looking
forward to learn more about
uh this fascinating paper
uh especially i'm interested in
exploring
uh phenomenological aspects of
bdi
belief desire and intention and also
to explore
somewhat more deeply the philosophical
underpinnings of
representation versus simulation aspect
of modeling
vdi in active inference
and
yeah that's it for me
great
let's uh begin with this more taxonomic
question
about the types of active inference
so we can think about the different
types that we've heard about in this
paper and elsewhere and then
whether or not we have something to
contribute about adding a specific type
to this list that will continue to grow
what does it mean or entail that we do
have
these different types so just to
review
in
this paper 46
they make a very clear upfront
distinction between what they
characterize as motor active mai and
decision active
and there's
a few differences
between motor and decision
who can list one category of difference
well the motor active inference doesn't
typically
require that you have to make a decision
it's more
a reaction or a reflective
form
uh as
compared to the decision active entrance
which does as the paper say
likely map over to the desire
question
yes
so
the motor ai
was connected to like motor reflex
are there decision-making reflex
does even if that's not
a classical usage like in the reflex arc
of the spine or something
moving the hand away from a hot surface
are there
cognitive refluxes
not really sure i i just i'm i basically
was asking in the
in the context of people who are writing
these papers now
who are bringing
the question down to a motor operational
behavior standpoint
how
breaking active inference up into
different classifications
is that in response to
a bigger problem which is
the behavior doesn't necessarily
um
behavior doesn't necessarily isn't
something that that's necessarily we're
able to conveniently um dissolve
down to or concentrate down into motor
operations
or or extensions or any of those other
different things that
that the writers tend to want to focus
on now
as opposed to
sort of the complexity and the variety
and the randomness of behavior
as a whole so
yes
great um so this is from page
81. oh yes i'll go for it
uh well i think uh the distinction
between
m a i and dai uh
is not
globally accepted among uh
well
various researchers
for instance uh if we look at the work
of
alan bertos
uh french
neuroscientist especially his book
i think it was called
the brain's sense of movement uh in that
book uh he actually
has a famous
code namely perception is simulated
action
uh and uh by this he means that he
implies that perception and
motion
and motion and perception or
thinking for that matter are irreducibly
interconnected
and so
the former
the former defines the latter
because of
the
intrinsic motricity
uh
of the creatures endowed with uh nervous
systems uh so i'm not sure if we can
distinguish between mai and dai in such
a
clear-cut manner
because as we know that
most motor
most
motricity and motor
or actions
are also
uh
pre-predefined in that perception or
many other thought processes
thanks dude
yes i i didn't know enough about
the
bdi model or the you know i'm still new
to the language especially of the
authors of this paper to the general
philosophy but you know i was talking a
lot about last week about the unified i
and higher order rules so if you want to
look like decision as higher order rules
and they would have some sort of uh
power like usually when we think of
consciousness in a unified eye
that makes decisions
and
we talked about eliminativism and the
implications of the equations are the
eliminativistic or not
and uh
yours is there what what direction does
the evidence take us
and so in terms of motor control like i
mentioned fodar's uh
modular mind
that it could be that uh
you know it's a threshold it's a free
energy principle
and it could just be action
action reaction
sense perception
and then a module of our mind sends you
know some perception of what however we
understand consciousness
that makes it appear to us like we made
a decision
[Music]
pardon me but that may not be accurate
that uh you know the equations might
hint that that's not actually what's
going on it's simply free energy
threshold being reached the threshold
could conceivably have
nothing or very little to do with the
decision-making process and it could be
post-facto like uh
the liebet experiments that uh the
perception like we made a decision
actually comes post-facto from the
threshold
cool thank you um also i think
uh adam saffron who had discussed those
libre experiments
does find a space for agency
if that's not to course of a
simplification but there is some
interesting ways to think about what
that experiment uh does or doesn't show
maybe we can return to that when we kind
of have
some figures and details dean
yeah i didn't know what you guys were
talking about with this unlimited thing
until i went back to the paper and then
i found this
and i'll just quote it we also this is
from the paper we also motivate a
squarely
non-eliminativist position with respect
to such constructs
and suggests that the set of theoretical
primitives out of which the active
inference models are built is sufficient
not only to recover the categories of
folk psychology but also to potentially
nuance them with more
fine-grained
distinctions so i don't i'm not sure
exactly dude what how what you've been
saying
either corresponds with that or not but
i'm i'm kind of curious
yeah go for it
yeah i mean to me it's a fallacy that uh
you know like a best of both worlds
fallacy that uh
materialistic research into
consciousness make
is that in reality my understanding of
the their conclusions of what they're
saying is that it is a limitivist and
they'll put a little statement in like
it's not a limited vist
but what does the evidence of their
models actually say
and can they actually
uh
program like a unified eye
and uh you put that did they eliminate
the unified eye
and it's just a bunch of perceptions
and various factors that reach a
threshold
and what does it mean
to uh
make a decision
so uh
and that's why i said do we just throw
away
uh thousands of years of dualistic
theology and uh
how people you know our whole lexicon
of uh
consciousness psychology comes from a
dualistic tradition
so if they're trying to grandfather in
these dualistic concepts
but even the evidence of what they're
saying
doesn't necessarily seem to warrant it
and then you know do they have the
courage
to be like no unfortunately the evidence
points to eliminativism
and go with that so i mean my impression
they kind of just throw in the statement
but it's unclear how how they're uh
you know how they're doing it because
the you know i guess you know it's going
to be unpopular to be an unlimited it's
kind of like the free will question
that i mean limitism also relates the
free will
but you know to stand up and be like no
i'm sorry free will doesn't exist that's
where the evidence is pointed
uh sort of put in there that they're not
trying to say that
but uh you know my impression i think
they actually are trying to say that
or that's where the evidence of their
conclusions are saying they just have
you know human weakness that doesn't
want to go so far as to follow the
evidence of
you know their research
interesting so just to continue on this
motor and decision ai so
page five
mai does not make decisions
once a decision has been made about what
to do
mai uses proprioceptive prediction
signals to move the body to carry out
the decided action sequence and
elsewhere we've talked about that sort
of set point
and then a transient suppression of
precision which allows the body to reach
this new spatial position
and also these models have tended to be
formulated in continuous time
whereas decision ai plugs in very nicely
to the motor ai
because it is explicitly considering
decision making and these higher order
rules
that
have to do with either
if you take a more realist perspective
what organisms or cognitive systems are
doing
or the more instrumental perspective
which is just this is how the the
process of decision making can be
modeled
and it's about what which decisions are
made about what to do in order to
generate some observations and not
others
and it's that
uh
focus on the observations that are
generated under different courses of
action and their evaluation in terms of
expected free energy that also ties it
closely to like perceptual control
theory
so that's the distinction they bring up
and
again in whether in the real world this
carves cognitive systems at the joint is
one question
in the world of the theories as
constructed
this is a clean separation
although as ali brought up that doesn't
mean that it's um
widely
accepted or even if everybody heard
about it that they would necessarily
agree with it
and there may be phenomena that are
mixtures and that's also why they talk
about the hybrid models where it's like
decision making at a higher level
and then motor at a lower level so that
could allow decisions about what section
of a face to look at or what section of
a page to read
and then that decision becomes
implemented in a continuous motor active
inference context through ocular motor
action dean
yeah
i'm not i don't think i'm
i don't think i'm leading with this
question about are we moving to a place
that says
that uh active inference will have
different types because i think that
there's different map there's a there's
math that's used in financial situations
those operations there's math that's
used in mechanical situations those
operations so i think it's it's a
natural byproduct of so how do you make
the math work
given the circumstance i don't think
that there's anything about this that's
saying active inference doesn't work
just because you want to make sure that
you're applying the proper formula
to the thing that you're trying to
describe but i do think it's interesting
that in order to be able to describe it
more precisely you just can't say
active inference you have to kind of
figure out what the math is
for the specific condition that we're
trying to analyze
yeah
definitely makes sense let's now move to
this lower part of the page on the
different adjectives that we've seen so
people can probably add or think of more
or even imagine there's so many
adjectives in the
in the textbook called the dictionary
we've talked about extended active
inference
which was addressing extended cognitive
features and phenomena
where there could be sort of a
offloading
which was when the adaptive active
entity is going to utilize something
that is
more like a notepad like it's offloading
memory onto the notepad and then the
entity is holding on to information
about how to seek that information
or on both sides of the interface there
could be adaptive active and so that was
like the sort of true
emergent extended cognitive processes
deep active inference and and citations
could be could be added didn't get them
for all
deep
was utilized to describe temporal depth
in terms of longer and longer time
horizons of considerations
this was really an important development
because it moved beyond the sort of one
shot
next step model of active
and help manage this trade-off between
considering time horizons
as well as taking action in the time
step that the entity is actually in
sophisticated active inference
and various other
um
cousins of it
utilized hierarchical modeling
which could have temporal depth at one
or multiple levels but doesn't need to
it it does and it could
but this is referring to like the
thickness or the hierarchical modeling
component
uh affective active inference which was
used by hespet all to refer to
uncertainty parameters
and some of the cognitive
interpretations of uncertainty
parameters as being related to to
valence
um and then there's others like
branching time active and um
it comes to what dean said which is
just saying like we use active inference
may not reduce uncertainty enough
any more than we used a linear model
whether just talking about it casually
or
writing the paper
more information has to be provided
and so this is sorting this is sorting
to uh starting to build
the taxonomy and the classifications and
the ways of communicating reducing
uncertainty okay you went to that
hemisphere but was it this continent or
that continent was it this coast or was
it that coast like zooming in
ultimately resulting in just describing
the particulars of the model that was
constructed ali
uh well adding to what dean has just
said uh well i don't think that these
different flavors and versions of active
imprints that have recently been
recently been branched up
they don't necessarily
concern themselves with different
situations or different niches
for example that last one branching time
active inference
uh well that was a very recent
uh version of active inference which was
uh
yes this is the paper uh they introduced
that and it's basically a more
efficient uh
computational approach to active
inference
and it's just the traditional active
inference but in a more
efficient out with a more efficient
algorithm to compute
the all the parameters needed
yes sometimes
it's these adjectives are describing
heuristics or implementations or
algorithms
other times they're describing the model
structure
other times they're referring to the
context that the model is being applied
to
like an extended cognitive system deem
yeah that's that's what i was going to
ask ali about so if i'm saying something
more efficient what am i saying it's
more efficient relative to
uh well relative to
the traditional approach to active
inference uh that has been proposed uh
for
the past decade or two uh and also uh
relative to
the other
um
the other approaches that are similar to
active inferences approach but not if
not exactly equivalent to it for
instance
reinforcement reinforcement learning
approaches and so on
okay and
one other
kind of analogy or mapping there would
be like
when a new variant of a neural network
architecture is introduced
there's a pomp and circumstance
to announce the novelty and the
relevance of this for somebody who's in
that field
similarly when there's a new variant or
a new focus whether model structure
model target or something else related
to evolutionary biology
sometimes a new word will come in
but then
that
new
target or model
structure if it becomes used
and it's sufficiently close that it's
not rejected from the rest of the body
of theory if it's an incoherent usage of
the adjective someone says well i made
you know simple active inference and it
has this totally different structure
that might not become incorporated into
the the network of active inference
models
whereas
if it does
become incorporated through its
theoretical compatibility or
utility and modeling that phenomena
or it's
presented in terms of a model
architecture that does apply elsewhere
the adjective kind of gets dropped and
then it just goes back to being neural
networks back to being active inference
back to being evolutionary biology
and then the field moves on and so the
the adjectives are just kind of like
another brick in the wall
dude
yeah i also mentioned last week i'm not
sure if it would go here in this section
is uh
the
purpose driven
purpose-driven behavior action or even
the
perception related to
a unified eye
and
even if it's on the pure level of sense
perception is it just that we have
uh you know these perceivers and they
perceive and then how are the signals
read
and uh
i mean it's easier to describe this in
an eliminativistic way whether we're
limiting or not uh in the for the
predictive mind is the main uh
struggles so to say between short-term
uh goals and long-term goals and then
you have to put in what axioms are we
making
is there some sort of uh for the higher
order rules if we assume that there's
some sort of rule that like an organism
acts in its own self-interest in its own
uh you know sort of say desire to
survive or to uh replicate and then you
the only struggle would be between
short-term and long-term actions like
you know god forbid here we have a
mosquito pandemic i was gardening and
got you know eaten up by mosquitoes and
it was just a sense you're replying to
the environment like i have an itch
should i itch it or should i have some
longer term that will go away quicker if
uh if i don't itch it and is that you
know something that's even in the
subconscious where just naturally i
would have an itch and i would itch it
but then i would somehow enter a longer
term decision making process
that
would tell me to act in a different way
and even terms for how i'm going to
interact
with the environment in the future let
alone something that might have a
moral or ethical
implication so if you have a simplified
model of just
where do we need purpose
for a sense perception to work and for
motor control to work even in terms of
reflexes because i think
you're just even on the motor control
let alone the decision-making uh where
does the decision making uh go and
what's the purpose
behind it and then how is that purpose
derived
yes so we can go to uh
targeted non-targeted
um
another
branch point is
i think this important question of
mapping from real world phenomena
and even
direct felt experiences like aesthetic
or just more generally phenomenological
and
anything about a formalism
and i'm not sure if i've quoted too
narrowly
but
they are writing that
intentions
so just to review the
uh bdi the beliefs and the desires come
together
and that is what generates the intention
there's the desire for the ice cream and
there's the belief that there's the ice
cream truck and that is what generates
the intentional behavior of like
pursuing the ice cream truck
intentions map straightforwardly to
policies with the lowest value for
expected free energy which is calculated
across different policies
policies are affordances that can be
taken
over a given time horizon so over time
horizon of three it's the combination of
affordances of length three
almost all other variables in the dai
model
are candidates for traditional
psychological beliefs
if being used to model the right kinds
of high-level cognitive processes
so what are the right kinds
but then later in footnote 5
this is distinguishing uh in
what they characterize as a different
reading of desire this reading is not
the thing that is desired but instead
about the transient presence of the
motivational force to approach the thing
we desire
so it's like why did you go there it was
my desire to go there what moved you to
go there desire
so it's almost like desire in the
specifics and then also seeing it as a
motivating force
but then they note
that habit might not have a direction of
fit and it illustrates another reason
consistent with our broader argument
concerning desires
not to assume that probability
distributions in the formalism must be
mapped onto beliefs the psychological
level
so
their candidates if we do it right
but it isn't an assumption
that they must be mapped onto beliefs
ali
uh well uh i wanted to mention uh the uh
uh a broader sense of the term
intentionality uh which i think the
heroes refer to because uh you see uh
for all the entities defined by uh
markup blankets and uh defined by uh the
existence of their mark of blankets and
their ergotic behavior uh well we need
an entity uh who can treat
an effect as being about its cause you
see
an entity who can
follow the direction from effect uh
to cause and um we also need an entity
who can treat an isomorphic map
as being about what it maps
or
let's say as oriented toward what it
maps well in both of these cases the
directionality or orientation
uh
can be referred to as
intentionality in its broad sense
so just to clarify this the second piece
you mentioned was
the entity
needs to be able to treat some sort of
isomorphic or structure preserving
mapping
as having an aboutness of the target
like the map of the city
translating that into the physical
movement and then uh there was a causal
inference question
entity can trace causes
such that they understand such that
they're doing some kind of causal
mapping
where agency is the belief that one can
be the cause
of
future aspects so is this agency
or is this
causal modeling
that could happen in the absence of
entity level agency
i think it's more uh it's a broader than
uh
necessarily being a cognitive agent uh
you see
it's any abstract entity
that can
[Music]
that can sketch out these kind of causal
relationships between
between the signs and
their either
uh icons or their
indices so
it's much broader and more abstract than
uh
necessarily cognitive agents
what kind of entities are you thinking
of
and is it manipulation and and that kind
of logical
uh juxtaposition no no the one uh
obvious example would be neural networks
neural nets uh we don't uh necessarily
bestow upon neural networks uh
cognitive agency right but they can uh
well match uh the uh
at least their input patterns uh onto
uh their uh output um
output indices
and it's um
these continuums of agency continuums of
cognitive systems it's like
easy to forget we're we're talking about
a cognitive modeling framework
albeit one that has a motor cousin
mai
and motor dev motor modeling history
because the mii distinction is um
also historical
like in terms of what which malls were
developed when
and uh
is this pan cognitivism
are we modeling everything as if it is
on the continuum of cognitive entities
like
i don't
know if it's as controversial to say
that a neural network is a cognitive
artifact
it might not be self-perpetuating or
embodied or have open-ended agency or
all these other features that some
cognitive systems have but
what makes it not cognitive if you meant
that
well probably the cognitive here uh
it was not a proper proper adjective uh
perhaps what i meant was uh to be
i don't know a kind of a conscious agent
or
but again on the uh
the subject of uh
using the adjective cognitive or neural
networks uh well there are quite a few
uh
[Music]
uh opponents uh to this characterization
for neural networks because uh they
believe that uh neural networks
as
uh agents
uh don't necessarily
uh decide on uh their
decide on their cognitive basis uh how
to
uh
map how to
you see map between the inputs and
outputs because
that's the difference between
representation and simulation if we uh
well uh
can differentiate between the between
those two
uh so probably yeah the more suitable
adjective here should be a conscious
agent
as opposed to cognitive agents
does that not take us extremely
far afield out of where we
um lose touch with empirical
measurements for example
and enter into important
philosophical questions but ones that
take us like
away from
our cognitive leg
and psychology perhaps even especially
folk psychology is sitting at the
intersection of cognitive systems
philosophical self-reflexive systems
so it's almost like a question of
this teetering stack
of folk psychology which way will it end
up falling
eliminativism perhaps is saying we'll be
able to dispense with classical
philosophical debates or some aspects of
them
by
just
moving everything that was folk
psychological into
a mathematical cognitivist framework
uh
well what i mean here is that well
the term intentionality
here
can also be used
in
in abstract models of active inference
and not necessarily
uh
well uh in the cases where we
unambiguously deal with
conscious entities that's what i mean
i think one of the
takeaways of this paper or one of the
implications of this paper
would be that
if
intentions
in folk psychology
are
beliefs plus desires
hashtag bdi model
and
beliefs and desires are identifiable
quantities in the academic formalism
then by constructing entities consistent
with the active formalism
it can be said that they have
intentionality because it could be said
that they have beliefs and desires
and so then it would only make sense to
call the behaviors arising from beliefs
and desires
to be intentional
so doesn't this uh conceptualization of
intentionality also subsume uh
the
more strict or narrow sense of that term
because well if we uh
in this sense if we uh infer
from
the the use of intentionality here
as as referring to only conscious agents
uh well in that case uh the um
the whole purpose of simulating active
inference agents uh
could potentially uh well raise some
questions
that's well uh i i'm not sure if i uh
could express myself
clearly on this matter or not but
oh no very interesting um dean and then
do it
so maybe amongst the three of you you
can help me with this because i don't
really keep up with the latest news on
neural nets but
if i
if i were to look at a neural net i
would assume that
most of those
nets are given
some kind of a target
even if they go out and forage for it
there is something about that but what
i've
been always been curious about is
especially in the in the context of this
paper
is that
if there is a target that's been
sort of linked to desire in this paper
and if there's
a curiosity aspect to the agent or the
net that's been sort of linked to
non-targeting
so if that's if that's one continuum the
orthogonal aspect of that also in the
paper is that there's
a rewarding
component say on the left of that
there's an information seeking or an
information an ambiguity component to
the right of that so here's my question
if
unless we say that
curiosity actually is a target
which this paper says is it's actually a
non-target and the operation and the
formalism actually points that out
then
how to set something up like a neural
net to actually be curious
because we we can be curious we can be
non-targeting
and
find reward in that if we go
one direction and find information
gained in that
in another direction and they are they
are completely different things they're
not
seen in the in the formalism as the same
thing so
i'm just curious whether
we're like because as i said i don't
know enough about neural nets to know
but
aren't neural nets constantly
constrained by having a target
i think there's many ways to
answer that
i am not sure if it would totally map
onto the difference of supervised and
unsupervised learning
like supervised learning being where
labels are provided
these x-rays belong to this patient
category these ones belong to the
alternate category i want you to get
really good but you know don't over
specify don't overfit
that distinction
supervised learning unsupervised
learning is more along the lines of like
here's input
according to how you're set up
embody
the statistical regularities and the
structure
of the information that has been input
okay and then that representation
allows like clustering and subsequent
analyses
or the addition of labels later
but it isn't predicated
in the training phase
upon the data or the cases being labels
does that
yeah but the predication is not
curiosity is it
that's my point is that there is no
curiosity in what you just described
right it's like a a pipeline
that is receiving whatever information
is being provided
and curiosity seems to kind of break out
of that
and it's like give me more examples
and then the directed curiosity would be
like i'm looking for more examples of
the label a
the undirected curiosity would be more
like
i just would like more examples
right so to
ask ally maybe ali is it consciousness
if it doesn't have curiosity
uh well um i don't think so because uh
you see uh even in uh
unsupervised learnings uh we don't
necessarily
well the neural networks uh don't
necessarily uh extract the uh
the
the essence of their training examples
what they do is all
is to extract
a statistical prototype of their tokens
the statistical prototype of their
training examples
so
actually
they can't recognize
a dog as a dog they just see patterns
they just see statistical patterns which
they've learned
through their
training process
so they're not
they're not necessarily conscious of
the object of dog or cat or whatever
what
what they try to do
is uh and in fact in some cases uh
well
sometimes we see that uh they have in
fact inferred uh wrong statistical
prototypes because of
well
insufficient training examples or
not appropriate training examples or so
on
but in any case uh what uh i don't think
we can uh
say that uh
well neural networks because uh
uh because of their ability to recognize
these patterns they necessarily
well
have consciousness because well
probably
in order to achieve consciousness
well other layers of
cognitive and even perceptual
mechanisms need to be deployed
good
i had some other points but if you
wanted to uh
you'll stay in the curiosity topic
um
and it's related to what the point i was
going to make about belief and desire
of you
clearly defining the words so if they're
specifically you know you're going to
take the bdi model
and use words like belief and desire to
uh
you know some relatively obscure
scientific model
versus
you know like a whole historical review
of the etymology
and uh
you know i mean and how do we how are we
defining
uh
beliefs and desire you know does
curiosity have a desire to learn
something
um
you know for its own purpose that that
means it's not goal
uh driven
and then how i would understand belief
and desire
in terms of
your so desires are biological urges
like uh your reproduction
or uh
survival and if of the emotions or maybe
all derivative uh how you're going to
put that out where if you're going to
try to source all of them from one pure
desire and all the other desires are
derivative if you're gonna have multiple
uh desires and then you'd have to have
some sort of waiting
function to await the different desires
and then beliefs are self-made
rules that come from our own
technician and that's where decision
making comes comes in and even you know
i think a rabbinic statement in terms of
free will that free will is implying
that you have the choice
to make the less desirous opinion the
the less desires choice like as a chess
player if you're thinking like uh
candidate moves and analysis trees that
in reality our candidate moves are just
how we control our body and you know do
we move our arm up or down
or the various controls of our physical
function
but you know what are the candidate
moves
and then how would the analysis tree
and
decision making is it you know how would
it come that you would make the less
desirous uh
decision is it purely you know let's say
short term uh verse long term and then
the organization of uh you know that's
like a system like okay i'm a jew i'm a
muslim i'm an atheist or i'm a
capitalist i'm a communist that we have
these self-directed
uh
beliefs that control our behavior and if
it's learning to do things like i can't
steal uh god forbid i can't rape i can't
kill and that like my desire if the body
tells me okay i see attractive woman uh
i want to have sexual relations
but then i have these beliefs like that
there's a system of rules and governance
that
is it purely because i can't get away
with it that i don't do it we don't rape
still and kill because uh
we can't get away with it or is there
this self-imposed moralistic uh behavior
and that's coming down to uh what belief
means
and then uh you know also if
you so curiosity you'd have to clearly
define
curiosity and if you're talking about
neural nets that you know can computer
just learn for its own sake uh and even
can a human just learn for its own sake
that
uh
you know we're participating in these
discussions purely because i enjoy
figuring things out even if it has no
practical implication
to uh you know some primal directive
of survival or reproduction or however
you're going to understand these primal
directives
and then uh
you know the equation be similar to a
chess algorithm for a computer where
uh it would appear that you could add in
weighting factors that you could program
this into the equations
and
you have some constants that would be
weighting factors so if you did have
just one primal directive of survival or
two primal directives
of uh reproduction and survival
and then you could give those weighting
factors
or you could have uh um a feedback
mechanism uh i mean with the environment
and and then
you know as i said where did the belief
comes in the self-made rules and then
how are those waiting factors calculated
in decision making and what does it mean
to make a decision is it possible that
we make the least desirous decision and
if we can't make the less desirous
decision uh you know do we not have free
will
thanks so jonathan shock made a great
point which is that deep neural networks
applied to reinforcement learning can
include curiosity as an explicit factor
it guides the agent to states which has
about which it has the most uncertainty
so it's a term which makes it rewarding
to explore currently unexplored states
and then just
um
to get provide a recent example
here's
a way in which a neural network
architecture was used
certainly worthy of more exploration
and
at a first pass or at least just
qualitatively one way to think about
that
and then we'll come to how curiosity was
described in the text is in active
inference we have a imperative for
action selection
that includes a pragmatic and an
epistemic component
whereas a pragmatic absolutist
perspective like reinforcement learning
needs to generate these modules and
alternate architectures
such that
information seeking curiosity
can be coerced into a reward framework
i mean what is the next question going
to be well it's rewarding to gain
information
oh what kind of information how much
information how are we going to learn
the parameters on our curiosity model
and so on and so active inference as a
first principles approach for this kind
of artificially intelligent system
allows us to include at the base level
both in objective
uh achieving
and a pure curiosity reducing element uh
dean and then we'll
look at how they talk about curiosity
thanks daniel so
as as is has directly been the case for
point twos
oh really just left and i was gonna ask
him this question okay i guess he's
still here um
so david when after uh got one
and now just what you were just sharing
with us here i
wondered without putting words in the
mark and i get a clarification i think
one of the things that you're
trying to make clear or
or at least bring
into the con
that
prioritization
which is the sort of the value waiting
aspect of how we see the world
is not
ordering the kind of placing of a
formalism down on paper that includes
rules like equals and plus and minus in
the fep or the sort of extended and
variation of energy
is that
and that's that oversimplifying what you
want us to make clear that
that having evaluating is not the same
that kind of prioritization is not the
same as being able to formally set down
an order
well i'm a dualist so like i'm i'm i'm
trying to i i think i could use these
equations for dualistic you know
purposes
and you could just factor in a weighting
factor
for these higher order rules and then
you know so my system would have some
sort of uh um
struggle between two separate realms of
material and spiritual realm so that's
you personally how i'm look i'm looking
at it but you know i could attempt to
understand it from
uh just the materialistic realm
and how the uh equations
uh you know would apply
and then if there's competing factors
what's the origin
of those competing factors so so if you
just put
your desires are biological
animalistic urges and beliefs are
self-created
rules of uh
cognition and then you want to have a
separate function like curiosity where
where
curiosity
maybe benefits the purpose of making
beliefs which would later come to become
higher order rules
and
or if you want to have the ability to
have
behavior that has no purpose
that you know i just enjoy understanding
things uh maybe that understanding will
help me make better higher order rules
um
and then even then saying oh like you're
saying for the equation here we have
these equations and it's free energy
and uh you know so the purpose
is to uh
minimize it minimize uh you know the
least action principle or eliminates the
limit energy usage and so if you're
looking like well why did i do that was
like you know dummy didn't you look at
the equation it was still it was the
free energy principle you did it to uh
minimize energy usage
and uh you know so we're just saying
that that uh
that's
you know the origin of all human
behavior from an
uh
sense
and uh you know from the folk psychology
that's what i said so i'm taking a
dualistic perspective where these higher
order rules are coming from a
non-material plane but i think they
could be modeled into the equations
thanks um also free energy minimization
doesn't entail the actual
minimal possible energy usage
though some people have made that
accidentally or intentionally a claim it
isn't what those equations as they're
being used here necessarily represent
but it could there could be a system
that thrives optimally based upon
reducing energy usage but also there are
situations where free energy
minimization and the path of least
action are not the lowest energy
consumption
um
is that short term versus long term
they're saying long term it is but it's
just short term versus long term uh
decision making in the
as opposed to a dualistic the predictive
mind that's saying it's not dualistic
spiritual versus material it's a single
materialistic and it's short-term versus
long-term
okay
let's think about that in the context of
of curiosity
um how they're describing so
uh
g
expected free energy of policies it's
like the policies are enumerated and
then g is calculated for them
reflects the inferred value of each
policy based upon beliefs
beliefs are p of o sub t
conditioned on pi so
the distribution of outcomes
conditioned upon policies if i go left
what do i expect to see if i go right
what do i expect to see that's a belief
and
the belief distribution about
observations conditioned upon hidden
states of the world
if there is food there then what
observations will i expect to see
and desired outcomes which is
as we've explored in 37
in user's guide there's this dual
implication
of the p of o distribution and active
inference
as what is expected as well as preferred
because
we reduce our surprise
about
the expected
slash preferred outcome distribution and
that is how the desired outcomes are
realized not by providing a higher
reward or value
to increasingly preferred states but
rather
treating the preference distribution
as expectations
which allows us to use supprisal and
surprisal bounding approaches
towards achieving
preferences
so how do they
talk about desire and curiosity
they're suggesting that these drives so
this is in earlier we talked about
there's the two ways to talk about
desire the specific target of desire as
a desire like i desire a cube of
tungsten or something and then there's
the drive that is associated with desire
what made the person do it desire in the
abstract
curiosity
drives discovery of what is not yet
known and thus has no preconceived
target
however one could also say that it has a
semi-formed concept of target because
one could be like
curious about something and then their
curiosity would be satiated by something
else
something but not something else so in
that case there was some of something of
a prior on what they were looking for
the claim that curiosity is not
cognitive so desire related
might seem suspect on the grounds it
could also be characterized as simply
the desire to learn
qualitatively
and this in turn could be conceived as
the desire that one's beliefs are as
precise as possible
even though especially in the short term
learning sometimes feels like it reduces
our precision
however the mathematics allow us to
motivate a genuine distinction here
specifically changing outcomes to
minimize the kl divergence in the risk
term in efe is a fundamentally different
sort of process for minimizing the
ambiguity term
so
the kl divergence is on the left side
here
and the ambiguity term is on the right
side here
here's equation 2.6 from the textbook
and it's it's in a different order
but just to see here's risk with the kl
divergence
and then here's expected ambiguity with
the h for the entropy calculation
um the latter
which is the ambiguity term does not
care how uncertainty is resolved so long
it is resolved
there's no preference for becoming more
confident in one possible belief over
another
whereas
the reduction of uncertainty
by
reducing the kl divergence is what is
bringing us into alignment with our
preferences slash expectations
hence that is a much more targeted form
of curiosity
in that it allows for
goal directed information seeking
and then they write at a minimum the
folk psychological concept of curiosity
corresponds to a very different type of
desire with a distinct counterpart in
dai
dean
yeah
that's perfect because what i wanted to
say was that i think that the curiosity
really points to that risk
and the reason i say that is because
you may find
that when the ambiguity is removed the
prize is a happy one or a not so happy
one and i think
that's
that's kind of important here to to see
sort of the
it's it's hard to say as it says here
it's however the claim the curiosity is
non-conduit it might seem suspect on the
grounds it could also be characterized
as simply
the desire to learn well that
before the learning
you you're you're sort of in a in an
ambiguous state will it be a happy
surprise or will it be an unhappy
surprise and so i think this this kind
of pulls that out
you
the the ambiguity applies a certain
amount of risk but then you have to you
have to act in the active inference
aspect of it to determine
whether or not the surprise will let the
other side of it is actually
good
or not so good
so i think that's where the curiosity
arm of this
comes to the fore it is non-targeted
until
it actually
has been
realized or somehow materialized
whereas the
the targeted stuff the desire stuff
and be part of your plan
i'm not sure whether the curiosity fits
as conveniently as the desire does
and just one short note on that is we
see a conditioning on policy
right
in a few different places so
it'd be interesting to think about where
does planning to learn
come into play
and in what ways is planning to learn
directed
or what if you plan to
have undirected learning
or all these other combinations david
yeah i'm not sure if it would exactly
fit in with the equations i'm thinking
here like maslow's hierarchy of needs
defined in terms of the free energy
principle
where um
you know so to say curiosity
requires
excess energy so if you're on the first
trunk of the hierarchy
that you have limited energy to apply
towards curiosity and if you do have
energy to apply towards curiosity you're
going to be best off to be curious about
things that will directly apply to you
know your security uh you know your food
or the primal uh directives as opposed
to uh
if you move up
up the hierarchy
of at least put this into maslow's
hierarchy where there you know there's
less risk associated with curiosity that
maybe you've achieved more
leisure activity and then and therefore
have more
um
energy to expand towards curiosity that
you could reach the highest levels of
massless hierarchy and focus on
your ideals and
what is the meaning of truth or
understanding
uh science
but it would still be
you know however you're defining the
free energy principle that you have some
sort of uh
conservation of energy and curiosity is
an expansion of energy
that uh
is limited uh but uh you know more
resources could be allocated so to say
energy resources to curiosity if it uh
makes the whole you know uh
unified uh your person more
more uh um efficient and you know they
become more secure more safe more social
except so and so on and therefore
they're more energy to expand towards
curiosity
thanks ali
i also think uh it might be helpful to
uh
mention the neural basis for um
these surprise appraisals because uh you
see uh
as we know we have two systems of
thinking system one system two famously
uh sketched out by uh
conor manning taversky
or
fast track and slow track of reacting to
stimuli
so
in the fast track
uh well uh
the stimuli uh bypass the sensory cortex
and go directly from thalamus to
amygdala right so uh our first reaction
our immediate
reaction to every surprise
uh would be something quite similar to
fear
but then after uh appraising that
stimulate stimulus
after going through the sensory cortex
and dynamic delay and then the
hippocampus uh then we can appraise uh
we can't evaluate that surprise as being
positive or negative
and
as a result of that we get a positive or
negative balance effect
so
in summary uh well every surprise
i mean either positive or negative it
could be at first at the very first
moment uh the um uh kind of
uh
negative uh
can induce a negative balance emotion in
us
yes i i brought in some of the quotes
from this paper um habitual and
reflective control in hierarchical
predictive coding
it's uh from 2021 and it's by king horn
millage and buckley
so they directly connect hierarchical
predictive coding architectures which
when they consider action have a lot to
do with active inference
in terms of thinking fast and slow like
you had just brought up
so they wrote on this view fast actions
may be triggered using only the lower
levels of the hierarchical predictive
coding schema
whereas more deliberative actions need
higher layers
we demonstrate that hpc can distribute
learning throughout its hierarchy with
higher layers called into use only as
required
so
that is very interesting when we think
about
going back to the mai dai distinction
from this paper
it's a hybrid model
albeit one where the motor spatial
control is continuous or modeled as
continuous
and then there's a more discrete
more mental or cognitive model that's
like thinking slow so it's almost like
there's thinking fast and slow even
within the mind and then there's
thinking with the body
and that's like even a lower level i
don't think even by thinking fast
they weren't talking about the reflex
arc
but there can be hierarchical modeling
even there
um
so
it uh
what are these
nested models
that are slower
how do those develop are they related to
the
physical architecture
of
our onboard
machinery
to what extent do they involve so many
of our offsourced
or extended cognitive phenomena like our
colleagues like our social networks
our books and learnings the social
structures that scaffold our beliefs and
so on
there's a lot of interesting pieces
there
um
what would be a good direction to go
in this second half of the dot too um
we had targeted non-targeted
is there anything there that's not
covered by the curiosity discussion is
there
oh unmute dean then yes go for it
sorry about that yeah i think we pretty
much okay
wrestle that one to the ground
okay do it
yeah my conception for targeted i'm
calling the unified eye
in terms of uh
you know maybe like the ant colony
where uh
if you
you could look at it like the ants are
all functioning
personally
with their own
uh your directive behavior and it just
works out that they're directed or or as
a unit but even like a human
whether there's a unified
um
of the human cells like even sense
perception that you know it's easier to
look at it like our
our uh um
you know like i mentioned we have 100
like almost 100 million cones and rods
in our eyes that are receiving photons
at every given instant and you just look
at it like they're active acting in a
unified manner
um but even that requires some sort of
targeted behavior that the you for even
direct motor
motor control
that our cells in our given body are
acting in a unified manner and could you
uh you take the free energy principle to
a cellular level
and say well
cells will act in a unified way
if it's in accordance with the free
energy principle but if it wasn't in
accordance with the free energy
principle then cells don't act in a
unified targeted way
and act according to their own levels
i'm not sure if you could take that to
the cellular level for
even things like sense perception motor
control like one arm wants to go this
way and one arm wants to go that way and
how do we have this unified control
it's it's interesting thing about what
would it what would make something
concord or not with fep because it's a
description framework
here is where in from live stream 25
with uh professor levin
here's even in the ant colony example
where different subsystem and and cancer
and and um like
other situations like biofilms were
modeled this way
that there can be coherence within each
tone
so to speak
uh
i don't know if this moves us closer to
understanding the experience of the eye
or whether there is in fundament
a unified eye
but
the cells in the nest mates body can be
understood as undergoing coherent
behavior
nest mates can the colony can
and then different people have taken
different perspectives on
what makes one level of analysis
more relevant than others like an
evolutionary perspective is that the
unit of selection is granted some
special power
a information processing perspective or
integrated information theory might
highlight what happens informationally
within and across levels
let's look at the air their um
dark room
experiment
we kind of
came to it a little bit last time but
what did anyone think their figure
and simulation
spoke to
how was it adding
details or
information that weren't present in the
more formalism and qualitative driven
other sections of the paper
i have a i have a question i don't know
if i have an
interpretation of it when others when
others looked at this
as it's now craft out
did they see ambiguity
removal or did they see
an entropy
question being resolved because
what i saw was the latter i i kind of
saw
that
something
something appeared with more information
gain
or something
disappeared if there was
no
sense that
that the
that the change of an ambiguity state
was going to make any difference so i'm
kind of curious what
others
how others interpreted the the actual
data as it as it laid out
post talk because this is all post hoc
this is just comparing 0.7.3.2.99.01
in terms of it is in terms of the
desired strength
and then i think they use the term
urgency in the paper
going
right
yes
well
on on the left side um okay so time is
there's uh time is moving from left to
right
there's a an entity that doesn't
desire they don't have a preference for
achieving ice cream
and in this simulation run
they observed that they were in a dark
room
and they picked the decision to flip a
switch
they then
went to the right
and they ended up
not finding
that they got ice cream
the weak desire agent first
flips a switch
and then
with higher confidence
goes to the left
and they end up realizing ice cream
in this case of the strong desire agent
even though they have uncertainty about
going left or right initially
they're in a hurry
or it's urgent
and they go left immediately
and that turns out that it does
achieve
getting the ice cream
one one note is like
these are only showing one run of each
of those simulations
so it's like
does the
no desire entity always go to the right
or is that a 50 50
how have people use the bdi to do
quantitative modeling of behavior
are they moving
their verbal and formal arguments from
above in the paper
into a form factor
that will
be more amenable or palatable
to people who are already using these
models to do
behavioral analysis
well i think the bdi
i mean strictly from the standpoint of
here's what we watched
this agent do
it kind of it kind of had a 50 50 choice
it was playing more in the geometry
space how this is represented is more
sort of the bayesian distribution piece
right so you've got a
percentage of of an area as you're
moving
from left to right that's either
darkened or
remains agnostic it doesn't it doesn't
sort of change
what
what the outcome or what the the
matching of an outcome and
the expected free energy are
so i think that it just brings more
information to the
to the observation of what's actually
going on when
when the lights either do go on or don't
go on because that first one
the lights don't go on i think and the
agent either stumbles
to the right place or doesn't
but they don't care
but i do think that what what happens
is
you can have geometry only or you can
have deep geometry and
a proportion or a distribution and i
think that's what this is
kind of laying out for us that you now
you've got more information
and with more information hopefully
you've got less
less uh
invariance you've got more variance
being described here than you would if
you left the vocal geometric bubble
alone does that make sense
yes
and uh they they follow up
after the figure
that this magnitude mapping
it's
giving not just some theoretical detail
to this
mapping
and they provide several citations many
recently with smith and others
um where it's used
in in many different contexts and then i
i kind of found it
uh
also interesting in the following
sentences after the paragraph that i had
just quoted there
this motivating force could be
corresponding to the magnitude of the kl
divergence
kl divergence
between the q variational distribution
of observations conditioned upon policy
divergence with
the preference distribution
p of up
within the expected free energy
so that's one of the terms that we've
looked at in the g of pi
i.e the risk term
not the ambiguity term with the entropy
this is because stronger preference
values over rewarding outcomes in p of o
of t increase the kale divergence
and lead the agent to seek reward over
information gain
so there's still a knob
maybe multiple that are slightly
interacting
there's a knob by which
more
pure curiosity that would be just the
ambiguity resolving
but undirected
mixtures of pure curiosity and directed
curiosity
weak preferences
with a lot of openness
and increasingly sharp
preference distributions
induce
increasingly urgent
pragmatic values seeking outcomes
and um
[Music]
there's a lot of
funny things that come to mind like
a question for one person might be a
survival question
for another it might be a research
question for another it might be like a
pure curiosity
um
where's the oxygen in this room
is that a survival question is that just
um
you know again are you researching
oxygen distributions in rooms so you
have a target to understand that or are
you just curious about that thought um
dean then do it
i think that i think daniel that clearly
speaks to what david and ali were both
mentioning in terms of so what's your
time frame here right
so you take off and you have a bird
strike and now you don't have enough
time
to
land anywhere
on the river
is that curiosity
it's that desire
is that what is that in terms of how
much time do you have now to manage
the risk
aspect of this
this situation that you now find
yourself under certainly survival
but yeah what what what percentages or
what proportions of each one of these
different
parts of the equation
are being calculated at any given moment
relative to the overall time frame that
you're now constrained under
so
yes dude
yeah we just look at the refrigerator
you know example that
well okay had i been curious
you know earlier during the day
about the layout of the room i might
have remembered how to get to the
refrigerator but i i didn't expend that
mental energy so here i am hungry
and i don't know my surroundings
and so you have the level of curiosity
could have provided benefit but now at
this point uh
uh you know you have the risk factor
will i injure myself or or
eat and i was thinking uh
you know like chess or something like
okay like i'm uh
the
alpha zero
is
programmed with the you know the most
powerful computers for hours and hours
to just understand the game
and then later it's able to take that
and win
uh so like as a person it's like okay i
really just like thinking about chess
and understanding the patterns but then
you know well i have to reproduce i have
to see to the success of my children
in the offspring i have to uh you know
make money and survive
and so you know maybe i could become a
professional chess player or something
like that but then you would come and
come in and well um if my goal is to uh
you know reproduce and see the success
of my offspring
and you know make money and survive
there's better methods to do that than
becoming a
professional chess player even like
active inference
that okay i'm curious about how this
stuff works but it's probably not going
to help me reproduce or make a living
and if i try to you know take my
curiosity about consciousness
and
use that to benefit reproduction or
making or making a living
it's unlikely
uh to
see that much uh
fruition
but at the same time the the
i mean the power of curiosities you
don't know how it's gonna benefit you so
the ice cream example you know if we if
we had a meeting in the kitchen you know
during the day and then we all go back
to our rooms to go to sleep and then
we're hungry at night the person who was
just curious about how the room uh was
laid out is going to be able to uh you
know likely retrieve the ice cream
without any injury as were the person
who didn't expand the energy to be
curious about the layer uh layout of the
room
uh may not achieve
uh the ice cream and that's why i like
in my in my own head it may not be you
know directly applicable to this paper
but it could be in folk psychology
uh it would be to
you know map this to something like
maslow's hierarchy of rules which would
be
in line with neural nets that there
would be some sort of
higher order rules and some sort of
ability to uh
put the expansion
of more energy like okay like i thought
about chess and now i'm winning and i've
achieved a little bit of social standing
or you know want a little prize money or
you know even school
i was curious about consciousness now i
got a bachelor's degree and i have
enough proficiency to you know get a job
and support a family
and now i could exhort even more energy
to it
but at the time of the pure curiosity
you don't know how it may uh you
actually benefit you in terms of reward
great
points that it's almost like jumping
through different hoops
what
it might be best accomplished through
pure curiosity
at a future time point
so in in again that survival research
and pure curiosity trilemma
there's times where being driven by one
or the other
helps us
move through complex real world
situations
if we knew
the whole story from the beginning
then we could just follow along
but
in a highly partial information world
where we don't want our priors
to
lead to ruin basically
then pure curiosity and research
help
bring things within our survivable limit
into information gathering spaces that
we wouldn't necessarily
have traveled to
limited resources i don't know if they
could program that also into the
computer also like the limit of
resources and if that
if you interpret free energy principle
in general to you'll be a definition of
limited energy resources
ali
uh well uh yeah adding to my uh
own previous comments about uh the
subject of consciousness and curiosity
i personally believe that the nature of
consciousness is ultimately
computational
so it's amenable to
modeling and
similar simulation but
we're we're just not there yet
but
well
one
possible approach to
to achieve such model could be
potentially the active inference
approach or other related approaches
but uh you see
curiosity is just one aspect of uh
consciousness and uh i think
it should it could probably be helpful
to distinguish between the artificial
curiosity
and the experience of curiosity or the
phenomenology of the curiosity because
what we see here is
the agent that simulates the artificial
curiosity uh and and not it's not
exactly
uh isomorphic with
the experience we get from our derived
to
our information seeking drives and uh
and in fact uh in this paper i think it
was in page
uh 28
yes
it's in page 28
that uh they state that uh
we have not addressed questions about
the structure regenerative model would
need in order to account for experiences
of beliefs and desires
uh so
well at least in this paper we're not
dealing with
the actual uh experience of curiosity
we're just trying to
somehow model uh and simulate the
artificial curiosity in fact this term
artificial curiosity is one favored by
carl priston himself in his various
other
lectures
yes very good point
and it relates to kind of the
experienced view from the inside
versus the behavioral modeling view from
the outside a curious particle or a
curious forager
might be engaging in some kind of
behavior but
that isn't
the same thing
as
experience of
but they do provide references to
other
uh work like including work that has
been discussed previously on live
streams with christopher white and ryan
smith
on report paradigms of consciousness
um as we kind of head towards the end
here
i thought this was very interesting in
the section before the conclusion 11
free energy principle and direction of
fit
and this is kind of a good
section to to carry out and
bring forward into our other discussions
on active
for any organism described by the fep
the description will contain an
implicitly normative state element about
the states the organism should be in
and can be described as having cognitive
desire-like direction of fit
so there's a
preference distribution
and as this paper is building up it can
have an interpretation
as desire being a targeted desire
even beyond the case
a forward-looking afford-looking
decision-making agents
not all bayesian beliefs in the fap
formalism are best characterized as
doxastic being about belief doxology
this perspective may expand upon current
discussion in the fep literature
where it is fairly prominent to discuss
as if beliefs in simple systems
whether a mere active entity like a
pendulum or
adaptive active entities and just say
well i'm not saying that it really
believes that it's acting as if it
believes that
that conform to the fep
here our point is they can also
equally be described as having as if
desires
belief entered the active
lexicon slash ontology
perhaps because belief is used also in
bayesian statistics where distributions
more generally are called beliefs
also disjoint from the phenomenology of
experiencing a belief but rather that's
just called belief updating
is like a
process in bayesian statistics
this paper
kind of closes the loop with belief
not towards phenomenology but stapling
together some of the bayesian
distributional usage of the term belief
with the doxastic
being about belief the aboutness of
those bayesian beliefs is the folk
psychological concept of belief
by making that mapping
and connecting the formalism as a whole
or at least in the
core equations like the f and the g
to the bdi model
it also allows them to identify which
bayesian belief distributions map to
belief in the bdi
and which bayesian belief distributions
map to d
to the desires
in the bdi
and so to the extent that somebody can
say
a system has an as if belief
implicitly in a folk psychological way
we can also talk about as if desires
and that
helps
partition
but not disregard the discussion around
what different systems experience the
classic you know what is it like to be x
but
it
at least according to this
argument and perspective authorizes
usage of
intentions and desires
intentions arising from basically the
combination of the beliefs and the
desires in the bdi
and talking about
octave systems as if they have desires
what is that simulation desirous of
and then using its beliefs and desires
to explain its intentional behavior
not the experience of intentionality
experience of belief experience of
desire but using them in this
view from the outside
more deflationary perspective so
that's quite interesting and i think
something that will be uh
we'll see how it
catches on
are there other sections that people
want to talk about or what
will they carry
forward into their
post-46
life
i think daniel a couple of things i
think the desire to think part that
you're just talking about there
i'm not sure that it's specific
in nature i think it's more
generalizable and and sort of that scale
free
never
[Music]
to
to some of the stuff that you've brought
up um
[Music]
i think that when you when you
when you start getting getting to know
active inference a little bit more and
i'll speak from personal experience
with a focus on a little bit of
sort of personal grooming you become one
heck of an attractive state and so
i think you might not make money off of
that but at this point but i think as
you get more comfortable with the kind
of being able to take the information
and uh
use it across a variety of different
situations it's um
it's actually is quite helpful i don't
think i'll i'll ever get rich off of it
at this point but it it is kind of
interesting how
it's um i think it is growing in terms
of the amount of attention that it's
getting so
that's kind of my
my two takes on this so far
so you're saying it might
influence fitness
i think it might down the road as long
as we have enough time scale
dude
you know i've been coaching chess for a
while and mostly to youth and i'm used
to explaining uh
somewhat you know these concepts like
you know i i
want you to say that uh
people who are just curious about chess
and how the patterns work and how the
pieces work often improve much faster
than people who desire to win
and that a lot of times people will
reach a certain strength and then uh
their curiosity diminishes and it's just
their desire to win which isn't enough
that you know it's just like i want to
spend my night thinking about these uh
patterns
uh versus like i really want to you know
win
and have some sort of practical benefit
from
my efforts so
uh you know i have my own
[Music]
personal you know goals that brought me
to active inference because i was
looking for my own tools to advance my
own research and came on to active
inference as a a method or tool that
even though i you know like
it appears that you know the majority of
people are using it for a different
purpose that i would be able to rework
it for my own purpose but because it's a
interdisciplinary study and like you
know i'm an engineer and like
engineering usually works that way
where someone has
professional certification they sign off
and you could expect that they did their
part right and it's going to work
and you could
you know attach that module to your
module and both modules are going to do
what they said they're going to do uh
and then you know the curiosity will do
i really want to understand how your
module works you know do i really care
about dean and ali's research or you
know do i just uh you know want to trust
that their module works and i'm going to
be able to attach that to my module to
uh you know make make something uh
more powerful and both are probably true
to you know to
you know limited uh energy uh limited
resources that uh you know that i would
like to understand dean and ali's module
to the best of my ability but energy uh
time allocation uh resources are are
limited uh but then you know certainly
if you had a module that would help my
module and we could plug them in
together and uh you create a more
powerful interface so that i'm bullish
about active inference uh and uh as a
framework
that will benefit uh you know the more
and more people who get involved and i'm
seeing my own direction in my own
research how uh you know i think this
will be useful and i even think uh
i got uh
jennifer i think joined the discord and
i mentioned it to a few other people
that that might be able to advance their
research and then try to understand uh
you know the current uh existing modules
uh you know that are that are out there
you know within the act of inference and
you know as i mentioned the first the
importance of interdisciplinary studies
for uh you know big issues uh you know
none of us are going to figure this out
it's going to take interdisciplinary
studies and none of us are going to be
able to understand all the disciplines
necessary
to piece together the bigger puzzle
nice thank you yes interesting point
about the uh
curiosity driven
learning
and how that can
[Music]
be like a
not even paradoxically more successful
approach or mentality to set off on a
learning journey
with
um
[Music]
i just think about somebody trying to
learn organic chemistry which i tutored
for many years
and people who set themselves up for the
pragmatic value
and said i want this outcome
sometimes they achieve the outcome other
times they didn't
but it set up a lot of psychology around
not achieving the outcome when it didn't
happen on the expected timeline
and a lot of like secondary cascading
failures
however
there's also the the clear counterpoint
which is but if we don't
want the higher grade
then
like if we're just going to be curious
about learning organic chemistry like my
finals in six weeks
so how are we going to balance the
timelines
and uh the curiosity and i think maybe
even this paper helped us look at one
way
which is
keep the preference direction
but understand how the urgency of your
preference
influences
the way that you take action
and
just think about what what if you what
if your final was tomorrow how would you
go about it okay now what if the final
was in 100 years how would you go about
it
where are we in that continuum
do we have time for curiosity and for
openness or is this an actual emergency
situation
and then we can triage where there is an
emergency organic chemistry situation
but also hold space for curiosity and
openness and even in the emergency there
has to be information seeking it's just
more directed information seeking okay
we're going to work through the practice
tests and that's what we're going to
have time for
there's still is going to be information
seeking but not of the same kind if we
had more time to kind of space out
even though in a alternate slash
preferable world perhaps that's the
better way to learn or the more fun way
to learn or
so on
any other
thoughts
uh well one of the things i really like
about
active imprints research is the
willingness of the researchers in this
area to
uh seriously address the criticisms
instead of just
dodging them and
their willingness to to constantly
improve and update the theory uh in
order to
fill the
fill the gaps and uh well
and
also
address the uh
uh well the weakness or any any weakness
or loophole uh in the in the theory uh
and that's uh very
uh it's liberating to see such uh active
area of research uh going uh
going forward uh
in a very determined and also very
open-minded and open-minded way uh and
uh well
that's one of the things i think
sets it apart from
other some other
research areas today
it's what we prefer it's what we expect
we're curious about it
okay
dean ali david thanks a lot for this fun
discussion and and ryan maxwell and alex
for this paper it really capped off a
long
run of live streams we've had
quite a nice sequence
going back to
the beginning of this year
getting through many many
discussions
next week we're going to have the
second quarterly
roundtable meeting
and then we'll have july off of
paper discussions
and we'll be coming back in august with
we don't know exactly what they're going
to be
but
we know some of them
and we have a few guest streams and
other streams coming up but
um
[Music]
yeah it's been a nice run the lab
meeting next week will be a great cap to
this
season slash semester
and then we'll come back for the end of
2022 with
some new changes that i think people
will be really excited about so
thanks everybody and see you later
thanks daniel
thanks everyone agree thanks a lot
you